Guide to the Jane Conlon Muller Oral History Collection AIA.012
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
- Paul O'Dwyer (1907-1998) (partial transcript included in two folders), 1990-1991
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 17 April 1991, Apr 17, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Keith Foundation. Formation of Irish American Labor Corps.19 April 1991Adoption between Ireland and U.S. Treatment of orphans in Ireland before adoption laws. Enactment of law that required people to be a resident of Ireland for one year in order to be eligible to adopt an Irish orphan. Effects of law. [10:00 - 20:00] Hunger strikes tenth anniversary. Elizabeth O'Hara requested O'Dwyer's help to organize large memorial service. Mickey Rourke's interest in hunger strikers. Bobby Sands' development as a poet and writer in prison.Irish radio shows in the early 1930s.Irish sweepstakes for the elimination of tuberculosis. Strategies for selling raffle tickets in the U.S. [20:00 - end] More on sweepstakes. Shipping tickets back to Ireland. Last of sweepstakes.Irish and Irish American radio. Berkowitz show. Contemporary shows. (Cd 22, Track 2)
    [09:35] Were you involved at all indirectly or directly in helping people adopt babies from Ireland?
    [18:40] Had he [Connie Neil] lived in New York?
    [19:14] How many books of tickets did he leave you with?
    [20:16] So the agents then expand across the miles, these numbered agents, they were also in Ireland? At least their centers were in Ireland?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 19 April 1991, Apr 19, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] Irish radio. Other ethnic shows. O'Dwyer's appearances on radio and television shows to inform people about situation in Northern Ireland.Irish singers and dancers. Transformation of Irish music into Irish American music. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Irish and Irish American music. Reviving the Feis - attempt to ban from competition "Tin Pan Alley" songs. Development of Irish music away from tradition. Development of the Irish Arts Center. [20:00 - end] Council of Bishops and attempts to help travelers. Bringing travelers to Geneva for UN conferences to state grievances against the Irish government.Irish Protestants committed to freedom for Ireland. (Cd 23, Track 1)
    [01:30] Do we know offhand who was the first ethnic group to have a radio show?
    [03:20] Why [was John McMichael murdered] ?
    [12:07] Was this because you were afraid of losing the traditional Irish music through this Irish Americanism?
    [16:19] Have you met her [Sinead O'Connor] ?
    [19:12] The Irish Arts Center also teaches things such as the flute, is that right? And other Irish instruments?
    [25:46] These people, the travelers, they never emigrate do they?
    [25:52] Do they come to New York?
    [26:15] How do they contact each other if they're moving around all of the time? They certainly don't have mailing addresses, or do they…?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 15 August 1991, Aug 15, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] Irish American History roundtable [sic, New York Irish History Roundtable] and its attempts to develop histories of the Irish American experience. 1832 book by John Quincy Adams about the history of the conquest of Ireland. Reasons for Adams' devoting so much of book to poetry. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Adams' book. Pope's and Henry II's involvement in the conquest of Ireland. Adams' biases.Sylvester O'Horan - gathered together the best historians of his time and published the History of Ireland in 1778. [20:00 - end ] John Quincy Adams' career and how he became president.O'Dwyer's desire to develop a college course on diplomacy with the City College of New York. Description of UN. (Cd 24, Track 1)
    [07:07] Where did Angela find the book, do you know?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 15 August 1991, Aug 15, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] United Nations activities. O'Dwyer's becoming a consul. His desire to find a way for minorities to become consuls. O'Dwyer's continuing attempts to create classes in diplomacy. Attempts to improve relations between the UN and the people of New York. Ellis Island medals and the exclusion of Irish and Italians from recipients. [10:00 - end] More on UN Activities. Ellis Island medals. Combating the insularity of the UN by creating meetings where UN representatives speak to the public. Strike at UN by Restaurant Associates seeking more money. (Cd 24, Track 2)
    [00:04] Around what year?
    [14:30] It's almost like the United Nations reaches out?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 25 November 1991, Nov 25, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] Appearance on PBS television show with Kathy Novac and Charlie Rose. Thoughts on retirement. Strategy for teaching young or inexperienced lawyers as an outside consultant for O'Dwyer and Bernstien. Views on hobbies. [10:00 - 20:00] More on O'Dwyer's hobbies/interests. Developing a wetlands preserve out of the swamp near his property in Goshen. Clearing the poison ivy from a cemetery, also near the Goshen property. [20:00 - end] More on O'Dwyer's hobbies/interests. Conclusion of poison ivy story. Visit to Ireland in September. Origination of idea for O'Dwyer Forestry Foundation to supply revenue for the maintenance of the O'Dwyer-Cheshire home. Attempt by A&S to construct a farm in Prospect Park, Brooklyn, but the company made no provisions for maintenance. (Cd 25, Track 1)
    [04:03] What next for Paul O'Dwyer? Will you retire when you are ready to leave this position?
    [05:46] To what extent will you go back to the practice of law?
    [07:56] Or the case that they were promptly working on and have it relate directly to that, rather than the overall advice, that's what you're saying?
    [08:24] Did you learn that way yourself?
    [08:27] And who taught you that method?
    [08:47] It sounds like you're looking forward to this.
    [20:05] Do you think they were all afraid of catching the poison ivy?
    [20:19] Why weren't you [afraid] if you were allergic to it?
    [22:37] What is this wash called, do you recall?
    [23:52] It falls under your category of 'activities' as you mentioned to me before. Your hobbies then fall under the category of 'activities' and they can be either on an intellectual, academic side or a physical side. There are many different things. Whatever interests you at the time?
    [24:18] Tell us a little bit about your recent trip to Ireland. I believe you were there in September?
    [26:44] A&S the department store?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 25 November 1991, Nov 25, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] More on trip to Ireland in September. Purchasing land for forest. Mary Higgins Clark planting a tree. Visits in Northern Ireland with IRA gunmen, victims, families of hunger strikers. Visit to O'Dwyer-Cheshire home. [10:00 - 20:00] More on trip to Ireland. Changes in management of O'Dwyer-Cheshire home. Irish countryside. Visits to Dublin and Dingle.Irish American situation in New York. Sean O'Casey's plays and their portrayal of prostitutes in Ireland in the 1930s. [20:00 - end] Levels of acceptability to Irish and Irish Americans at different times and different media. Dancing at Lughnasa, a play. Biography of John McBride, novel with heroine having two children with lover while still married. The Commitments, a movie. (Cd 25, Track 2)
    [06:30] So the French pocket was outside of Roscommon?
    [06:40] And this all took place in September?
    [10:42] So now they're allowed to be part of their own management and have more control over their own affairs and their lives?
    [14:34] Which sister is this?
    [15:59] Right off the side of the main part of town?
    [17:07] What is it today that's currently bringing the Irish and their relatives out en force?
    [18:10] Isn't that back in the 1920s and 1930s?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 25 November 1991, Nov 25, 1991; [00:00 - end] Reasons why most illegal Irish immigrants come from Dublin. Education of recent immigrants. Views of Irish born vs. Irish Americans on Northern Ireland. Irish and Irish American authors. NGOs in UN and a seminar planned where the Northern Ireland question will be brought before the UN. (Cd 26, Track 1)
    [01:07] What do they [the Irish] come out for to New York en masse? We started to discuss Dancing at Lughnasa, which is the recent paly that is currently being performed at the Plymouth Theatre by the Abbey Theatre Players.
    [05:54] Tell us please about what is happening on December 9 this year.
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 16 November 1990, Nov 16, 1990; [00:00 - 10:00] McBride principles. Difficulty in passing bill through state legislature. Influence of British on William Brown. Tom Hayden introducing bill. Governor Duke Machin vetoing bill. [10:00 - end] More on McBride principles. Success of bill in Florida the second time it was introduced. Continuing work on passing the McBride principles. (Cd 27, Track 1)
    [06:36] Do you know exactly who he [William Brown] was wined and dined by in London?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 16 November 1990, Nov 16, 1990; [0:00 - end] More on McBride principles. Founders of principles. Effectiveness of principles in identifying guilty companies and bringing them bad publicity. (Cd 27, Track 2)
    [00:35] When did the McBride principles start?
  - Paul O'Dwyer (on Michael Flannery) - undated, [00:00 - 10:00] O'Dwyer speaking about Flannery. FBI taping conversations. Flannery's character - Devout Catholic. Member of IRA during War of Independence. Severity of Irish Civil War. Concept of free state of Ireland. Flannery in United States - employment, lifestyle, devotion to Irish independence, reputation, trial. [10:00 - 20:00] Description of five defendants in conspiracy trial. Differences between Flannery and Harrison. Description of trial. Insistence that U.S. government had approved of arms trade. Perjury of CIA agents.St. Patrick's Day Parade committee. [20:00 - end] More on St. Patrick's Day Parade committee and controversy surrounding Flannery's nomination to be Grand Marshal of parade. (Cd 32, Track 1)
    [16:46] What time frame was this?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 15 May 1991, May 15, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] Discussions based on Muller and O'Dwyer looking at files from the 1940s.Letter from Tom O'Connor, writer for newspaper PN, about West Indian people with Irish surnames. O'Dwyer challenged O'Connor's position that the people did not deserve to have Irish names. Story of O'Dwyer's meeting a black man with an Irish name when he was working on the waterfront in NY when he first arrived in the U.S.Television program about hate and different aspects of hate. Story of meeting Tommy Evans. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Tommy Evans -British sea captain who ran arms to Ireland before War for Independence and befriended O'Dwyer. Evans' desire to retire to Sailor's Snug Harbor. [20:00 - end] More on Tommy Evans. O'Dwyer's help in getting him in Sailor's Snug Harbor.Crime in New York City. History, ethnicities that were involved in criminal behaviors, association with poverty. Irish prostitution at the turn of the century. (Cd 34, Track 1)
    [00:49] What does PN stand for?
    [07:23] You had never met a black man with an Irish name before?
    [10:02] Is that the area that was known as Hell's Kitchen?
    [14:32 ] The English prisoners?
    [19:17] Where was it [Sailor's Snug Harbor] located?
    [19:42] So it was actually a home for old sailors, is that what we're talking about?
    [19:56] Because he never sailed on an American vessel?
    [27:41] Are you talking about Irish women and prostitution?
    [29:30] They were coerced into a brothel when they came off the ships, is that what you are saying?
    [30:06] In other words, he would shelter them in the church. What about young men?
  - Paul O'Dwyer - 15 May 1991, May 15, 1991; [10:00 - 20:00] History of Irish in New York City. Development of Irish Americans into a wealthier class, spread to suburbs, growth of Irish American population. [20:00 - end] More on history of Irish Americans in New York City. Boarding houses, parochial school education, Irish politicians, predictions for Irish politics in future, ethnic pride and how to be a good American. (Cd 34, Track 2)
    [00:00 -10:00] More on Irish American crime. Rise out of poverty and into society. Effects of poverty on Irish American community. Five Points neighborhood.Irish Americans in politics. Discipline in schools.[08:20] Would you offer an alternative to that kind of discipline?
    [09:11] Did your own parents demand discipline to a point?
    [27:45] So, what you're predicting then is any politician, not just the Irish, are going to have to go for human rights in general and not have it attached to any nationality or any race that eventually will all really will melt together?
- Michael Flannery (1902-1994), 1991
  The two interviews with Michael Flannery were recorded in January and December 1991 in his home in Jackson Heights, Queens. Flannery focuses mainly on his experiences in Ireland as he recounts his childhood, joining the IRA, serving in the War for Independence and the Civil War, and being imprisoned for two years. But Flannery also discusses much of his life in the U.S., including founding and resigning from Noraid, being charged with gunrunning for the IRA, and being Grand Marshal of the St. Patrick's Day Parade.
  - Michael Flannery - 14 January 1991, Jan 14, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] Flannery's early experiences. Where he was born, his education, family, his mother's experiences in America and his impression of it as a child. [10:00 - 20:00] Escaping the British army and joining the volunteers (who would later become the IRA) in 1916, options for a career, experiences in the IRA. [20:00 - end] More on IRA experiences. Reasons for joining, how he survived, staying at loyalist houses. (Cd 28, Track 1)
    [00:18] Could you tell me when and where you were born?
    [00:44] What was the name of the town or the village that you were born in?
    [01:19] Who were your parents?
    [01:33] And where were they born?
    [02:02] How long was your mother in America?
    [03:14] So, when she went back, how old was she then, when she first went back to Ireland?
    [03:42] Did she know the man that she met and eventually married before she came back or did she meet him when she came?
    [03:52] So she must have gone back and forth a few times to America and Ireland?
    [04:07] Tell me some more about your family if you can.
    [04:34] Were they all boys before you?
    [04:46] Did your mother and father work? Or did you live on a farm?
    [05:07] Did you help them as a child growing up? Was it your job to work on the farm also growing up?
    [05:16] And what kind of schooling did you have?
    [05:56] So you mentioned college, so you had a college education then?
    [06:02] What subjects did you learn, what did you specialize in, in college, what was your degree in?
    [06:27] How many years of schooling did you actually have?
    [06:46] Were you taught English or Irish?
    [07:00] Did you speak Gaelic in your home?
    [07:19] Had you heard about America when you were in Ireland as a child?
    [07:33] Where did your mother live in America?
    [07:42] Where did they live in America?
    [08:41] What were your impressions? Were you impressed when you heard the stories about America?
    [09:45] Do you remember your first job in Ireland other than work on the farm?
    [11:54] So if you had stayed at the monastery that could have changed your whole life?
    [13:26] Were any boys taken from the monastery?
    [13:50] Who would actually take them?
    [14:11] And then what would they do with the boys?
    [15:45] They would never train the young boys, as in other countries, to become members of their armies or anything?
    [16:15] Other than the IRA, did you have any other job in Ireland?
    [16:30] You lived at home then, until that time [when he left Ireland for America] ?
    [17:19] So you did this [volunteered for IRA] now from the age of about 16 to 25, is that correct?
    [19:12] You were how old when you first joined?
    [19:18] 14 during the 1916 rebellion. Then you were well aware of what was going on?
    [19:53] Why do you feel you wanted this [to join volunteers] so young? Who influenced you to join the volunteers?
    [20:43] Were there other members of your family that also belong [to the volunteers] ?
    [21:07] So it was the family thing to do then in your situation?
    [23:43] So then you were actually paid probably a salary?
    [24:15] Who fed you?
    [24:52] Did you travel usually with a companion or with other members or did you travel individually mostly?
    [26:06] Did you have specific locations, farms and houses that you knew would be safe havens?
    [26:42] What is a loyalist house?
    [28:14] What would you say? You'd say, "I'm a member of the IRA - can you put me up?" Was it that simple?
    [28:22] And if they said no?
    [29:28] Did you have to go into any of these houses with arms?
  - Michael Flannery - 14 January 1991, Jan 14, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] End of Black and Tan War. Treaty signed in 1921. Republican opposition to Treaty of Limerick. Division of Northern Ireland from the Republic of Ireland. Discussion of Civil War and division throughout the country. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Civil War. Reasons why Britain wanted to remain in Ireland. America's support of Britain during Cold War.Experiences in IRA. Organization and strategies of IRA. Ambushing the British. Views on killing British soldiers. [20:00 - end] More experiences in the IRA. Organization, how it operated, rules and regulations, differences from other armies, ranking within the army. Flannery's first raid. Spies betraying IRA, especially ex-British soldiers. Flannery being captured. (Cd 28, Track 2)
    [00:13] Now you did this until you left. You left Ireland in 1927 you said. Why?
    [00:56] That was the year of the Black and Tan War?
    [06:50] You actually had a location then?
    [07:00] Can you spell that word, the Dail?
    [07:43] What is his name [surviving member of the Dail] ?
    [07:47] And he's in Dublin now?
    [08:07] How many people were involved in the army, during the time of the treaty, that were opposed?
    [13:51] You might have other anecdotes that you want to talk about of your days as a member of the IRA? What territory did it bring you to? How far in the country did you travel?
    [16:56] Where did you get your arms?
    [17:33] What did you do for your change of clothes?
    [17:55] So you would go home occasionally to get replenished?
    [18:24] It wasn't an easy life at all, was it?
    [18:33] Did you find it exciting?
    [18:38] Do you think you had to be young to live this kind of life?
    [20:16] What percentage of men if you know, would have been members of the IRA of the Irish community?
    [23:39] Would they send you reinforcements if needed?
    [23:52] Did you have a rank when you left Ireland?
    [24:28] How many were in a column?
    [26:07] Do you remember your first raid?
    [26:55] How old were you?
    [27:02] So you had trained for a while before you actually did it?
    [27:53] How did that happen [spending his 19th, 20th and 21st birthdays in prison] ?
    [27:56] Were you captured in the middle of a raid or an ambush or just you were in the wrong house or the wrong place?
    [29:45] How did you get captured?
  - Michael Flannery - 11 December 1991, Dec 11, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] Celebration of Flannery's 90th birthday. Reluctance to celebrate birthdays, anniversaries, etc.History of problems in Northern Ireland. Unity vs. disunity. Success in unification of Irish people in 1916. [10:00 - 20:00] More on Black and Tan War. Negotiations with Britain. Formation of two armies in Ireland. Outbreak of Civil War in 1921. Second Dail. 1969 attempts by Republican army to get members elected into Parliament. Formation of the Worker's Party. [20:00 - end] Communicating with the IRA while in America. More on America's support of Britain remaining in Ireland. President Bush and Reagan's support of England. Sinn Fein attempts to take over Dail. Division of Republican movement in America and Ireland. Founding and split in republican movement in U.S. Resignation from Noraid in 1986 and formation of new republican Sinn Fein organization. (Cd 29, Track 1)
    [00:49] So are they planning a big celebration for you, for your 90th birthday?
    [00:57] Do you happen to know where it's going to be held, since it's not a surprise?
    [01:16] What is the date of your birthday?
    [02:45] How did you celebrate your feast days?
    [03:08] So this is a personal thing between you and your wife then to celebrate only your feast days? Do you have other friends who do this also or this is strictly between you and your wife?
    [03:33] Was this passed down to you?
    [03:50] Was this just your idea between the two of you or did you get this idea from some sort of family tradition?
    [05:18] Don't you think that most people feel that celebrating their birthday - it's an event, it's a special occasion, it draws attention to somebody, to an individual, and they're special for that day.
    [05:53] When you were growing up in Ireland as a young man, was your birthday celebrated in your home? Did your mother and father make a fuss over you?
    [06:47] But still that made it special, different from any other day?
    [06:53] Tell us about the time from about 1969 when political changes were taking place in Northern Ireland.
    [12:38] At what time was this?
    [14:39] Whose barracks?
    [19:11] At what time frame did he start this Worker's Party?
    [19:29] You were living here in this country in 1969. Yet, you were very well informed about exactly what was going on in the North of Ireland.
    [21:47] There's been a direct line then between you and the IRA in the North of Ireland all this time, and there continues to be?
    [27:06] When you say divided us...?
    [28:20] You said that you founded Noraid in this country 20 years ago. Could you tell me exactly when?
    [28:55] You were active then, the whole time up until 1986. What was your main focus and purpose?
    [29:59] Could you please explain what the Dail actually is?
  - Michael Flannery - 11 December 1991, Dec 11, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Noraid. Founding, purpose, and activities of Noraid. Methods for sending money to Ireland. The organization losing prestige in America in recent times. [10:00 - 20:00] Corruption in the American government and lack of political support for Irish.Reluctance of other countries to help Ireland because there's not enough economic benefit. Flannery's being put on trial for lending money to send arms over to Ireland. [20:00 - end] More details about Flannery's trial. Other defendants, lawyers representing defendants, U.S. government's involvement in helping send arms over to Ireland, charges brought against Flannery and other defendants. (Cd 29, Track 2)
    [02:40] How did you ensure the fact that the money you sent from this country got into the proper hands over in the North?
    [03:26] And how did you check on that [that the money was going to people who needed help] ?
    [04:59] Who did this fumigating?
    [05:25] So the constant communication was through letters as well as people travelling back and forth informing both sides what was going on. What about telephone contact?
    [05:52] How did you know that [your phone was tapped] ?
    [06:26] Who do you think was tapping your telephone?
    [07:14] This is the Noraid office you're talking about?
    [07:18] How did you feel about this?
    [08:10] Are there any other functions of Noraid besides what you've mentioned?
    [08:50] You're talking about by population?
    [12:14] Isn't it a fact that there aren't that many Irish politicians put up these days for office?
    [13:53] What specifically do you feel would be a good method to stop the drug infiltration into the United States?